A Finding Aid to the Sandra Berler Gallery Records, 1970s-2013, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Sandra Berler Gallery records
1970s-2013
Archives of American Art
Sandra Berler Gallery
Berler, Sandra
AAA.sandberl
Archival Resource Key
5.5 Linear feet
The Sandra Berler Gallery records measure 5.5 linear feet and date from the 1970s to 2013. The collection sheds light on the gallery's operations through administrative records, artist files, exhibition files, and photographs.
Biographical / Historical
The Sandra Berler Gallery was founded in Chevy Chase, Maryland in 1975 by art dealer and photography critic Sandra Berler. The gallery specialized in twentieth-century photography, exhibiting contemporary and vintage U.S. photographers, including Bruce Davidson, Helen Levitt, Jerome Liebling, Margaretta Mitchell, and Nickolas Muray. The gallery also exhibited and sold international work by Mexican photographers Manuel Alvarez Bravo, Flor Garduno, Graciela Iturbide, Austrian photographer Inge Morath, and French photographer Jacques Henri-Lartigue.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as three series.
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1970s-2011 (Box 1-2; 1.1 linear feet)
Series 2: Artist Files, 1974-2013 (Box 2-5, OV 7; 3.8 linear feet)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1970s-2002 (Box 5-6; 0.6 linear feet)
Scope and Contents
The Sandra Berler Gallery records measure 5.5 linear feet and date from the 1970s to 2013. The collection sheds light on the gallery's operations through administrative records, artist files, and exhibition files. Administrative records advertising and publicity files, invoices, receipts, consignment records, papers from Sandra Berler's involvement in the Association of International Photography Dealers, and some newspaper clippings. Artist files consist of correspondence related to the artist's work, biographical summaries, writings, price lists, photographs, negatives, slides, and more. Exhibition files include price lists, catalogs, announcements, loan documents, and some photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Sandra Berler in 2017.
Photography; Art galleries, Commercial -- Washington (D.C.); Women art dealers
- Administrative Records, 1970s-2011; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1.1 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Scope and Contents
  Found here is correspondence with other galleries and museums, collectors, and various organizations regarding the sale or loan of photographs, lectures by Berler, exhibitions, and some personal matters from friends and colleagues. Association of International Photography Dealers files include correspondence, printed material, event and membership ephemera, and price lists. Files relating to Magnum Photos include correspondence, trade material, some exhibition material, and clippings. Reference files labeled photogravure and Mexico primarily include printed material and notes, but also contain price lists and scant correspondence. Also found here are articles written by Berler for the Washington Print Club's newsletter.
  - Advertising and Publicity, 1978-1999; Archival Resource Key; 1 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Art Dealers Association of Greater Washington, 1997-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Association of International Photography Art Dealers, 1981-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Association of International Photography Art Dealers, The Photography Show, 1993-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Berler, Sandra, Articles for Washington Print Club, 1984-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Berler, Sandra, Correspondence, 1970s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Book Orders, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Collections, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Conservators, Decorators, Installations, 1980s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Consignment and Loans, 1982, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Donations, Cornell University, 1981-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Magnum Photos, Inc., 1975-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Mexico, Reference File, 1988-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, 1970s-1980s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photographs to Buy or See, 1980s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Photogravure, 1980s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Printed Material, Clippings and Articles, 1980s-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Printing, 1991-2005; Archival Resource Key; 2 Electronic discs (CD) (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Artist Files, 1974-2013; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 3.8 Linear feet Box 2-5, OV 7
  Folders might contain correspondence related to the artist's work, resumes, writings, price lists, copies of photographs, snapshots and slides, sales records, inventories, and exhibition material. Files for Bruce Davidson, Sandra Berler's brother in-law, include reviews of the book completed in conjunction with his exhibition at Berler Gallery, Time of Change: Civil Rights Photographs, 1961-1965 (2002).
  - Abbott, Berenice, 1986-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Adams, Ansel, 1993-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Arnold, Bill, 1984-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bravo, Lola, 1993-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bravo, Manuel Alvarez, 1976-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Callahan, Harry, 1994-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Carnochan, Brigitte, 1999-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clergue, Lucien, 1975-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Clift, William, 1976-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Collier, John Jr., 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Davidson, Bruce, 1980-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Davidson, Bruce, Book, Time of Change: Civil Rights Photographs, 1961-1965 (2002), 2002-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Davidson, Bruce, Library of Congress, 2008-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Davidson, Bruce, Printed Material, 1970s-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
  - DeLory, Peter, 1981-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Donaghy, Don, 1994-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Edgerton, Harold, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Engel, Morris, 1984, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Epstein, Mitch, 1986-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Erwitt, Elliot, 2003-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Evans, Terry, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Faurer, Louis, 1985-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Fellows, Caroline Whiting, 1989-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Frankel, Godfrey, 1986-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Freed, Lenard, 1995-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Garduno, Flor, 1991-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Gedney, William, 1980-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Gibson, Ralph, 1998-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Goldberg, Jim, 1994-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Goldberg, Joel, 1985-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Halverson, Karen, 1988-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Hayden, Jacqueline, 1987-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Hechinger, John, 1978-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Iturbide, Graciela, 1992-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - James, Christopher, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Kertesz, Andre, 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Klipper, Stuart, 1983-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Koudelka, Josef, 1988-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Lartigue, Jacques-Henri, 2002-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - Levitt, Helen, 1986-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Levitt, Helen, Printed Material, 1988-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25-26)
  - Liebling, Jerome, 1983-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27-28)
  - Mackenzie, Maxwell, 1994-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Mark, Mary Ellen, 1991-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Matter, Herbert, 1978, 1982, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Maurer, Neil, 1979-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Mayes, Elaine, 1978-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Metzker, Ray, 1981-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Meyerowitz, Joel, 1979-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Meyerowitz, Joel, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 7)
  - Mitchell, Margaretta, 1986-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
  - Morath, Inge, 1975-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  - Morowitz, David, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Moster, Lida, 1982-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Muray, Nickolas, 1992-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
  - Nettles, Bea, 1981-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Pare, Richard, 1997-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Rantoul, Talbot Neal, 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Riboud, Marc, 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Robbins, LeRoy, 1974-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Rothschild, Gayle, 1987-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Salgado, Sebastiao, 1999-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Schwarm, Larry, 1989-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Shaw, Allison, 1997-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Siskind, Aaron, 1990-2004; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Smith, W. Eugene, 1994-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Spohr, Barbara, 1980-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Tice, George, 1994-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Vestal, David, 1992-2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Walker, Diana, 1996-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Weegee, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Wood, Brian, 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Yampolsky, Mariana, 1993-2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10-11)
  - Yampolsky, Mariana, Printed Material, 1990s-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Mexican Women Photographers, 1992-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Mexican Photographers, 2000-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Artist Biographies, 1980s-2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15-17)
  - Artist Correspondence, Mixed, 1975-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Exhibition Files, 1970s-2002; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 5-6
  Found here are price lists, exhibition catalogs and announcements, loan documents, newspaper clippings, and correspondence for several of the gallery's exhibitions. The Japan exhibition file includes correspondence and contact lists related to a potential show, and the exhibition idea file is composed of printed material, mostly exhibition announcements from other galleries, catalogs, clippings, notes, and some photographs.
  - Swimmers (1984), 1984-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - India Observed (1986), 1982-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Coney Island (1987), Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Tio Photographers (1988), Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - No Trumpets, No Swans (1988), Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - On The Wing: Photographers Inspired by Flight (1990), 1990-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
  - Check to Check/Social Dancing (1992), 1991-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - The New York School Photographs, 1936-1963 (1992), 1992-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Frida Kahlo Diego Rivera: Photographs (2002), Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Japan Exhibition, 1992-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Exhibitions Ideas, 1970s-1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 8)